<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Immersion Screenwriting]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Immersion Screenwriting]]></description>
        <link>https://thegrid.ai/thestorydepartment/</link>
        <generator>The Grid</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 22:27:32 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://thegrid.ai/thestorydepartment/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 22:27:28 GMT</pubDate>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Loglines Are Incredibly Important]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h1>Why Loglines Are Incredibly Important</h1>,<article><img src="https://imgflo.herokuapp.com/graph/2b2431f8e7ba7b0/709fd2ef45c2765ce32a2897d124ce2f/noop.jpg?input=https%3A%2F%2Fthestorydepartment.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2017%2F04%2FLogline-It-Event-3.jpg"><h1>5 Reasons Why Loglines Are Incredibly Important</h1><p>Loglines can predict failures. This week, I watched a movie where the writer had not adopted critical notes. The film failed. I&apos;m not saying that it would have succeeded if he had heeded the advice. If only things were that simple. The draft I read could be summarised in a one sentence logline.</p></article>,<p><strong>Loglines can predict failures. This week, I watched a movie where the writer had not adopted&nbsp;critical notes. The film failed. I’m not saying that it would have succeeded if he had heeded the&nbsp;advice. If only things were that simple.</strong></p>,<p>The draft I read could be summarised in a one sentence logline. Based on that logline, I predicted the film would fail.</p>,<p>I am not the only one who makes snap decisions based on the logline alone. In fact, EVERY busy film executive does this – every day. And everyone I know in&nbsp;the film industry works incredibly hard to make a living. They&nbsp;have&nbsp;absolutely no&nbsp;time to waste.</p>,<p>Within this&nbsp;context, loglines are the only tool that allows you to make decisions quickly, and efficiently.</p>,<p>Many writers think they can write loglines. The truth is that only a very few understand this very specific skill. If more writers did, there wouldn’t be so many flawed concepts floating around. I’m not talking about execution now, merely premise.</p>,<p>I have been studying loglines for a long time now, and five years ago I decided to launch&nbsp;<a href="http://logline.it/">Logline It</a>. Since then, it has grown into&nbsp;the leading website and a community dedicated to the promotion of effective loglines. Today, we have over 4,000 loglines on the site, and over 20,000 reviews to learn from.</p>,<p>Thanks to this site, many writers have perfected their loglining skills, and are now able to judge early on whether they have a story idea that could fly.</p>,<p>A properly written logline allows you to make a reliable snap judgment on the prospects of a project. This is one reason&nbsp;why the logline is the most powerful instrument to gauge the quality of a screen story.</p>,<h3>1. A Snap Decision Tool</h3>,<p>The logline is the smallest recognised industry format that allows gatekeepers to make snap decisions. Based on it, they may&nbsp;either eliminate a concept from their list, or allow it to jump to the next level (usually the synopsis).</p>,<p>For this reason, loglines are the most common summary&nbsp;in trade publications at the most important annual film markets:&nbsp;Berlin, Cannes, Sundance, Toronto, AFM.</p>,<h3>2. Loglines Test&nbsp;Uniqueness</h3>,<p>A properly written logline describes a screen story uniquely. Using three key story elements, it triangulates a film so effectively, it will differentiate your project&nbsp;from every other film made, or story told.</p>,<p>Using the power triangle of&nbsp;<em>main character</em>,&nbsp;<em>inciting incident</em>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<em>story goal</em>, you lay the basis of the logline – and&nbsp;that of your film’s 3-act structure.</p>,<h3>3. It Shows Inherent Structure</h3>,<p>Following the right logline format, you will give the reader an exact idea of the key information that&nbsp;will be conveyed&nbsp;in your story’s first act, and a promise of what may be expected in act two.</p>,<p>Most writers who don’t understand this, capture only about the first ten minutes of their story. They’re not to blame; most teachers don’t understand the function of a logline, and teach a format that is way too loose.</p>,<h3>4. Loglines Express The Writer’s Vision</h3>,<p>Until you understand your story thoroughly, it is impossible to write a logline that does service to it. For this reason, it often&nbsp;takes weeks, sometimes months before a writer is happy with their logline.</p>,<p>By the time the script is finished, the writer MUST be capable of conveying the essence of his/her story in one sentence.</p>,<h3>5. Loglines Are A Guide Through Development</h3>,<p>Robert McKee talks about the Controlling Idea, and John Truby discusses the Premise Line, but neither are particularly useful when you have to create them yourself.</p>,<p>These gentlemen provide us with extremely vague&nbsp;guidelines, and their examples fail completely and utterly in capturing&nbsp;<em>consistently</em>&nbsp;what is unique about the films they describe. While some of their examples hit the mark, others don’t. This proves that their approach is not systematic, not reliable – and therefore useless for the working writer.</p>,<p>I’m proud that I have developed a format that is used by&nbsp;<em>every professional writer</em>&nbsp;who has studied with me. Some use it as a basis to build&nbsp;their own version, but they all stick to the foundation I teach,&nbsp;because it is so simple and at the same time effective.</p>,<p>A properly written logline not only helps you capture the essence of your story, it guides you through the writing process. It helps you make tough decisions during development, and ultimately keeps you on track.</p>,<p>If you don’t already master this skill, it’s about time you get to it.</p>,<p>Test your own logline during the&nbsp;<em><a href="https://logline.it/celebrate-5-years-logline-it-live-event/">Logline It</a></em><a href="https://logline.it/celebrate-5-years-logline-it-live-event/">&nbsp;fifth anniversary event</a>!<br><a href="https://logline.it/celebrate-5-years-logline-it-live-event/">More details here</a>.</p>,<p>Happy Loglining!</p>]]></description>
            <link>https://thegrid.ai/thestorydepartment/why-loglines-are-incredibly-important/index.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">3c1316a5-85bd-46b8-b9a7-745058929f96</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 22:27:01 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Collection of Exciting New Booze Books]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<article><h1>A Collection of Exciting New Booze Books</h1><p>It seems like just about everyone has a cookbook, cocktail manual or spirits&apos; history guide out on the market. A lot of superb ones cross our path with regularity-from new to old -but some really set themselves apart. Most recently we&apos;ve been digging through four new offerings and each is very different from the next.</p><img src="http://assets.coolhunting.com/coolhunting/2016/03/03/large_cocktail-booze-books-cool-hunting.jpg"></article>]]></description>
            <link>http://www.coolhunting.com/food-drink/four-new-booze-books-2016</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">0fc54023-4bf7-4487-b1f5-b6e04236ebd3</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 01:57:53 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>